Guide to the Henry Margenau Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1927-1990; Series II
  - Articles
    - Physics, 1927-1974
      - "Line Broadening of an Impurity Spectrum in Silicon" [with Douglas Sampson], 1956 (Box 4, Folder 110)
      - "Magnetic Moments of Odd Nuclei" [with Eugene Wigner], 1940 (Box 4, Folder 111)
      - "The Meaning of 'Elementary Particle,'", 1951 (Box 4, Folder 112)
      - "Microwave Conductivity of Slightly Ionized Air,", 1959 (Box 4, Folder 113)
      - "Natural Width of K#-Lines,", 1934 (Box 4, Folder 114)
      - "Nonadditivity of Intermolecular Forces" [with J. Stamper], 1967 (Box 4, Folder 115)
      - "Normal States of Nuclear Systems" [with Dana Warren], 1937 (Box 4, Folder 116)
      - "Note on Pressure Effects of Band Spectra,", 1936 (Box 4, Folder 117)
      - "Note on the Calculation of Van Der Waals Forces,", 1931 (Box 4, Folder 118)
      - "Note on the Quantum Dynamical Correction of the Equation of State,", 1932 (Box 4, Folder 119)
      - "Note on the Validity of Methods Used in Nuclear Calculations" [with Dana T. Warren], 1937 (Box 4, Folder 120)
      - "Nuclear Energy Levels and the Model of a Potential Hole,", 1934 (Box 4, Folder 121)
      - "On Film Formation of Water Flowing Through Thin Cracks,", 1945 (Box 4, Folder 122)
      - "On the Forces Between Positive Ions and Neutral Molecules,", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 123)
      - "On the Interaction of Closed Shells" [with Philip Rosen], 1953 (Box 4, Folder 124)
      - "Physical Processes in the Recovery of TR Tubes,", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 125)
      - "The Physics and Semantics of Quantum Measurement: A Reply to Prugovecki" [with James L. Park], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 126)
      - "Pressure Broadening on the Inversion Spectrum of Ammonia,", 1949 (Box 5, Folder 127)
      - "Pressure Effects of Foreign Gases on Sodium D-Lines" [with William W. Watson], 1933 (Box 5, Folder 128)
      - "Pressure Effects of Nitrogen Potassium Absorption Lines,", 1933 (Box 5, Folder 129)
      - "Pressure Shifts of Krypton Lines" [with William W. Watson], 1937 (Box 5, Folder 129)
      - "Progression of Nuclear Resonance Levels with Atomic Number,", 1934 (Box 5, Folder 130)
      - "Quantum Dynamical Correction for the Equation of State of Real Gases,", 1931 (Box 5, Folder 132)
      - "Quantum Mechanical Description,", 1935 (Box 5, Folder 133)
      - "Quantum Theory of Line Broadening by an Ionic Plasma,", 1955 (Box 5, Folder 134)
      - "Quantum Theory of Spectral Line Broadening" [with Stanley Bloom], 1953 (Box 5, Folder 135)
      - "Relativistic Magnetic Moment of a Charged Particle,", 1939 (Box 5, Folder 136)
      - "Relativity and Nuclear Forces,", 1936 (Box 5, Folder 137)
      - "Resonance Interaction Between Deuterons and Alpha-Particles,", 1935 (Box 5, Folder 138)
      - "The Role of Definitions in Physical Science, with Remarks on the Frequency Definition of Probability,", 1942 (Box 5, Folder 139)
      - "Role of Quadruple Forces in Van Der Waals Attractions,", 1931 (Box 5, Folder 140)
      - "Second Virial Coefficient for Gases: A Critical Comparison Between Theoretical and Experimental Results,", 1930 (Box 5, Folder 141)
      - "Shift of the Transmission Band of Silver by Cold Working,", 1932 (Box 5, Folder 142)
      - "Simultaneous Measurability in Quantum Theory" [with James L. Park], 1968 (Box 5, Folder 143)
      - "Stark Effects in Line Broadening" [with Marvin Lewis], 1957 (Box 5, Folder 144)
      - "Statistical Theory of Radiative Processes in Plasmas,", 1966 (Box 5, Folder 145)
      - "Statistics of Excited Energy States of Nuclei,", 1941 (Box 5, Folder 146)
      - "Structure of Spectral Lines From Plasma" [with Marvin Lewis], 1959 (Box 5, Folder 147)
      - "Surface Energy of Liquids,", 1931 (Box 5, Folder 148)
      - "Tachyons,", 1969 (Box 5, Folder 149)
      - "Theory of High Frequency Gas Discharges" [article in four parts; part III is missing]
        - I. "Methods for Calculating Electron Distribution Functions,", 1948 (Box 5, Folder 150)
        - II. "Harmonic Components of the Distribution Function,", 1948 (Box 5, Folder 151)
        - IV. "Note on the Similarity Principle,", 1948 (Box 5, Folder 152)
      - "Theory of Magnetic Resonance in Nitric Oxide" [with Allan Henry], 1950 (Box 5, Folder 153)
      - "Theory of Plasma Radiation" [with P. Malozzi], 1966 (Box 5, Folder 154)
      - "Theory of Pressure Effects of Foreign Gases on Spectral Lines,", 1935 (Box 5, Folder 155)
      - "Theory of Pressure Effects on Alkali Doublet Lines,", 1958 (Box 5, Folder 156)
      - "Theory of Pressure Shifts of HC1 Lines Caused by Noble Gases" [with H.C. Jacobson], 1963 (Box 5, Folder 157)
      - Über die Verënderlichkeit der Anzahl dreier Metallelektrinen mit der Temperatur, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 158)
      - "Van der Waals Forces,", 1939 (Box 5, Folder 159)
      - "Van der Waals Forces in Magnetic Fields,", 1951 (Box 5, Folder 160)
      - "Variational Theory of the Alpha-Particle" [with Warren A. Tyrrell, Jr.], 1938 (Box 5, Folder 161)
      - "The Zeeman Effect in the Cerium Spectrum Between 3000 and 5000A,", 1927 (Box 5, Folder 162)
      - Zeitschrift Für Physik [three articles in German] (Box 5, Folder 163)
        - "Zur Theorie der Moleklarkrafte bei Dipolgasen,", 1930 (Box 5, Folder 163)
        - "Zur Abweichung vom Ohmschen Gesetz bei hohen Feldstarken,", 1930 (Box 5, Folder 163)
        - "Die Abweichungen vom Ohmschen Gesetz bei hohen Stromdichten der Sommerfeldschen Elektronetheorie,", 1929 (Box 5, Folder 163)
  - Books
    - Einstein's Space and Van Gogh 's Sky, 1982
      - Background material [includes material from Miracle of Existence ] (Box 6, Folder 164)
      - Correspondence
        - General [majority from John Archibald Wheeler], 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 165)
        - Publisher, 1979-1984 (Box 6, Folder 166)
      - Reviews, 1979-1984 (Box 6, Folder 167)
    - Ethics and Science, 1964
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 168)
        - Nagel, Ernest, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 169)
      - Reviews [includes several responses by Margenau], 1964-1981 (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - The Mathematics of Physics and Chemistry, 2nd Edition [review], 1956 (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - The Mathematics of Physics and Chemistry, Vol. II, [reviews], 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - Measurement in Quantum Mechanics ["Some Comments on…"; book was never published], 1971 (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - Miracle of Existence, 1984
      - "An Afterthought,", 1985 (Box 6, Folder 174)
      - Reviews and notices, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - Open Vistas, 1961
      - Correspondence [with Yale University Press], 1962-1980 (Box 6, Folder 176)
      - Reviews, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - Perspectives in Quantum Theory [draft of a chapter called, "The Logic of Noncommutability of Quantum Mechanical Operations and its Empirical Consequences"], 1971 (Box 6, Folder 178)
    - Physics and Philosophy, 1978
      - Correspondence
        - Bunge, Mario, 1976-1981 (Box 6, Folder 179)
        - Publisher, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 180)
      - Drafts
        - Autobiographical introduction, undated (Box 6, Folder 181)
        - Preface, undated (Box 6, Folder 182)
        - Handwritten pages, undated (Box 6, Folder 183)
      - Reviews, 1978-1981 (Box 6, Folder 184)
    - "What is Scientific Method" [chapter in unidentified book], undated (Box 6, Folder 185)
  - Discussions, 1934-1972 (Box 6, Folder 186)
  - Speeches, Lectures, Symposia, 1950-1987
    - "Anatomy of a Sacred Cow" [Connecticut College], 1956 (Box 7, Folder 187)
    - "Bacon and Modern Physics: A Confrontation" [conference commemorating the 400th anniversary of the birth of Francis Bacon, Pennsylvania], 1961 (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - "Causality" [Florence, Italy], 1968 (Box 7, Folder 189)
    - "The Common Denominator of Science and Religion" [Carleton College, Minnesota], 1957 (Box 7, Folder 190)
    - "Elegance as a Criterion of Validity in Science" [Rollins College, Florida], 1960 (Box 7, Folder 191)
    - "ESP in the Framework of Modern Science" [American Society for Psychical Research Forum on Extrasensory Perception], 1966 (Box 7, Folder 192)
    - "Ethics and Science" [International Conference on the Unity of the Sciences], 1977 (Box 7, Folder 193)
    - "Evidence of Teleology in Scientific Theories" [Sicily], 1977 (Box 7, Folder 194)
    - "For Lars" [Eulogy for Lars Onsager, Yale University], 1976 (Box 7, Folder 195)
    - "Fusion or Fission: Can the Art of Living Together Prevail over the Science of Destruction?", 1953 (Box 7, Folder 196)
    - How Science Finds Truth and Reality — With Some Thoughts on Religion [Star Island Conference], 1954 (Box 7, Folder 197)
    - "Integration in the Sciences" [Cleveland, Ohio], 1950 (Box 7, Folder 198)
    - "Introduction" [Fulbright Conference], 1962 (Box 7, Folder 199)
    - "Ionization Phenomena in Gases,", 1959 (Box 7, Folder 200)
    - "The New Faith of Science" [University of Wichita, Kansas], 1953 (Box 7, Folder 201)
    - "The New View of Man in his Physical Environment" [Michigan State College, Michigan], 1955 (Box 7, Folder 202)
    - "Note on the Calculation of Exchange Forces" [Office of Naval Research, Washington, D.C.], 1951 (Box 7, Folder 203)
    - "Objectivity in Quantum Mechanics" [Delaware Seminar on the Foundation of Physics], 1967 (Box 7, Folder 204)
    - "The Philosophical Legacy of Quantum Mechanics" [Washington, D.C.; Amsterdam], 1977 (Box 7, Folder 205)
    - "Philosophy of American Science" [University of Tokyo], 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 206)
    - "Philosophy of Science" [Florence, Italy], 1968 (Box 7, Folder 207)
    - Propriétés Optiques et Acoustiques des Fluides Comprimés [Bellevue], 1957 (Box 7, Folder 208)
    - "The Role of Natural Philosophy in Multidisciplinary Research and Teaching,", 1979 (Box 8, Folder 209)
    - "The Role of Scholarship in an Age of Science" [University of Wyoming], 1964 (Box 8, Folder 210)
    - "Science and Philosophical Perspectives" [Science Symposium, Fort Monmouth, New Jersey], 1966 (Box 8, Folder 211)
    - "Science and Society" [public talk at Town Hall, Los Angeles, program plus text], 1956 (Box 8, Folder 212)
    - "Science in Perspective" [Gerstein Lecture, York University, Toronto], 1967 (Box 8, Folder 213)
    - "Science, Philosophy and Religion" [Dalhousie University, Halifax], 1960 (Box 8, Folder 214)
    - "The Scientific Basis of Value Theory [Conference of New Knowledge in Human Values], 1957 (Box 8, Folder 215)
    - "The Search for Meaning in a Senseless World" [Hartwick College, inaugurating Margenau Lecture Series], 1967 (Box 8, Folder 216)
    - "The Search for Meaning in a Troubled World" [Hadley Lecture], 1975 (Box 8, Folder 217)
    - "Some Thought on Science and the Doctrine of Creation" [Duodecim Theological Society, New York], 1955 (Box 8, Folder 218)
    - "The Teaching of Science" [Pennsylvania State University], 1960 (Box 8, Folder 219)
    - "Theoretical Physics and Biology" [Versailles Conference, Institut de la Vie], 1967 (Box 8, Folder 220)
    - "Theory of Pressure Shifts of HC1 Lines Caused by Noble Gases" [Israel Conference; includes notes, drafts, some correspondence], 1961? (Box 8, Folder 221)
    - Untitled talks
      - Artificial Intelligence and the Human Mind [symposium, Yale University], 1986 (Box 8, Folder 222)
      - The Nature of Concepts, Their Inter-Relation and Role in Social Science [proceedings of the Stillwater Conference, Oklahoma], 1950 (Box 8, Folder 223)
      - Oberwalfach Symposium, undated (Box 8, Folder 224)
      - Remsen Bird Lecture [Occidental College; program only], 1956 (Box 8, Folder 225)
      - Spontaneous Phenomena [conference, Cambridge University], 1967 (Box 8, Folder 226)
      - Whitman College Lectures, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 227)
  - Other
    - "Ancient History of Physics,", undated (Box 8, Folder 228)
    - "ESP and Statistics,", undated (Box 8, Folder 229)
    - "Methodology" [essay in application for funds for the Foundation for Integrated Education], undated (Box 8, Folder 230)
    - "What is a Probability Field?", undated (Box 8, Folder 231)
    - Untitled
      - Notes and equations, undated (Box 8, Folder 232)
      - Unidentified handwritten manuscript, undated (Box 8, Folder 233)
      - Annotated writings of others (Box 8, Folder 234)